Finding Aid for Robert L. Potts papers, 1923-2005
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Robert L. Potts papers 1923-2005, 1967-2002
Potts, Robert L.
1 oversize folders
1 oversize volumes
6.5 linear feet
85524 Aa 2; Ac
Robert L. Potts was a community organizer, educator, and Episcopal priest. The Robert L. Potts Papers documents his many professional obligations, including his community endeavors in Detroit, his service within the Ann Arbor Public Schools, and his involvement with the Episcopal Diocese of Michigan.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was received from Robert L. Potts (donor no. 5318 ) in multiple accessions beginning in 1972; additional files came from Ethel K. Potts (donor no. 7075 ) in August 2011.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Robert Lester Potts was a community organizer, educator, and Episcopal priest. He was active in both Detroit and Ann Arbor. Born on January 28, 1923 in Muskogee, Oklahoma to Beatrice Onque and Howard William Potts, he completed high school in Kansas City, Kansas before earning his A.B. at Lane College (Jackson, Tennessee) in 1945. He spent the next two years as an officer in the United States Air Force, with duties in Biloxi, Mississippi and Hampton, Virginia. He was ordained as a minister of the Methodist Church, serving in Tennessee, Illinois, and Michigan from 1948 until 1963. In this time, he earned a Master of Divinity from Garrett Theological Seminary in 1952 and an honorary doctorate from Lane, where he had previously served as college chaplain and instructor of religion and social sciences.
After briefly serving as President of Texas College, in 1964 Potts was ordained as an Episcopal priest by the Diocese of Michigan. Potts served the city of Detroit over the next four years, including tenures as Executive Director of the Citizens' Committee for Equal Opportunity and coordinator for the Mayor's Youth Opportunity Program.
In Ann Arbor, he directed the Model Cities Program before his 1970 appointment as Ombudsman for the Ann Arbor Public Schools. His chief responsibility in this capacity was to mediate public grievances to the school district. He maintained these duties after he was promoted to Assistant Superintendent for Human Relations & Community Services, a position that he held until his retirement in 1986. In this time span Potts also earned an Ed.D. from the University of Michigan in 1975.
Potts served fifteen years as a member of the clerical staff of St. Andrew's Episcopal Church in Ann Arbor. In addition, the Diocese of Michigan installed Potts as an Archdeacon in 1988. He spent the next fifteen years of his life serving on the boards of countless philanthropic organizations, most notably the Shelter Association of Ann Arbor and Avalon Housing, Inc. Potts died on December 23, 2004 at the age of 81.
The Robert L. Potts Papers documents his many professional obligations. It includes his community endeavors in Detroit, his service within the Ann Arbor Public Schools, and his involvement with the Episcopal Diocese of Michigan. Speeches, reports and executive board meeting minutes constitute much of the archive.
The collection is arranged into four series: Personal/Family, Civic Organizations, Ombudsman, and Episcopal Priest. It is important to note that photographs and correspondence are nested within the various series.
Subjects:
African Americans--Michigan.; Clergy--Michigan--Detroit.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Race relations.; Detroit (Mich.)--Race relations.; Detroit (Mich.)--Social conditions.; Episcopal Church--Michigan.; Housing--Michigan--Detroit.; Metropolitan Detroit Citizens Development Authority.; Potts, Robert L.; Youth--Michigan--Detroit.; Youth Opportunity Council (Detroit, Mich.); Civic improvement--Michigan--Detroit.; Public schools--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Subjects - Sound Recordings:
African Americans--Michigan.; Episcopal Church--Michigan--Detroit.; Potts, Robert L.; Cathedral Church of St. Paul (Detroit, Mich.)
Contributors:
Potts, Randy.
Genre Terms:
Sermons.; Sound recordings.
- Personal / Family
  The Personal/Family series contains biographical materials and items pertaining to the Potts family. These include obituaries, newspaper clippings, family photographs, and correspondence. Also of note is an oversize scrapbook that features Potts's handling of the racial strife experienced in the Ann Arbor Public Schools during the 1970's.
  - Biographical Materials 1984, undated (Box 1)
  - Diplomas (Box 1)
  - Military Records 1946, 1947 (Box 1)
  - Awards, Certificates, and Recognitions 1976-2005 (scattered) (Box 1)
    (see also oversize folder)
  - Vital Records 1923-2004 (scattered) (Box 1)
  - Clippings 1968, 1986 (Box 1)
  - Telegram from Detroit Mayor Jerome Cavanaugh 1967 (Box 1)
  - Obituaries 2004, 2005 (Box 1)
  - Texas College 2004 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1982-1995 (scattered and undated) (Box 1)
  - Family
    - Ronald K. Potts (son)
      - Vital Records 1960-1993 (scattered) (Box 1)
      - School 1984, undated (Box 1)
      - Work 1983-1991 (scattered and undated) (Box 1)
      - Letters 1979-1992 (scattered and undated) (Box 1)
    - Randolph Potts (son)
      - School 1980-1994 (scattered), 4 folders (Box 1)
      - Professional 1981-1999 (scattered) (Box 1)
      - Letters 1990, 1992 (Box 1)
    - Robert O. Potts
      - School 1989, 1994 (Box 1)
      - Ann Arbor Transportation Authority 1980-1995 (scattered and undated) (Box 1)
      - Manuscripts 1988 (Box 1)
      - Card undated (Box 1)
    - Ethel K. Potts (Box 1)
    - Family Photographs (Box 1)
  - Scrapbook 1970-1987 (Volume 1)
    (include clippings, awards and miscellaneous)
- Civic Organizations
  The Civic Organizations series is subdivided between Potts' activities in Detroit and in Ann Arbor. The former reflects records of the Metropolitan Detroit Citizens Development Authority, of which Potts was an Executive Committee member, and the Mayor's Youth Opportunity Council, which Potts chaired as a direct response to the Detroit riots of 1967. A considerable proportion of the files pertaining to the Youth Opportunity Council contain photographs of Detroit youth engaged in an array of educational and social activities. The second subdivision holds materials that focus primarily on his concern for affordable housing in Ann Arbor, as demonstrated by his being a founding board member of Avalon Housing, Inc.
  - Detroit
    - Metropolitan Detroit Citizens Development Authority
      - Administrative
        - Articles of Incorporation 1966 (Box 1)
        - By-Laws 1968 (Box 1)
        - Board of Directors undated (Box 1)
        - Executive Committee Meetings
          - 1967 (Box 1)
          - 1968, 4 folders (Box 1)
          - 1969, 4 folders (Box 1)
          - 1970, 3 folders (Box 2)
          - 1971, 2 folders (Box 2)
          - 1972, 3 folders (Box 2)
        - Annual Meetings 1969, 1972, 2 folders (Box 2)
        - Chairman's Report to the Board of Directors 1967, 1971 (Box 2)
        - Executive Director's Report 1970 (Box 2)
        - Vice President's Report 1972 (Box 2)
        - Executive Director's Presentation at Wayne State University 1968 (Box 2)
        - Letter to Executive Director 1969 (Box 2)
        - Administrative & Operating Committee Meetings 1969, 1970 (Box 2)
        - Memos 1971, 1972 (Box 2)
        - Procedure for Project Ratification undated (Box 2)
        - Nominating Committee 1968 (Box 2)
      - Financial
        - Statement of Revenues, Expenditures, and Financial Conditions 1967 (Box 2)
        - Financial Report 1968 (Box 2)
        - Financial Forecast 1968 (Box 2)
        - Audited Financial Statements 1967-1971 (scattered) (Box 2)
        - Projection of Cash Requirements 1970 (Box 2)
        - Cash Forecast 1971 (Box 2)
        - Balance Sheet 1972 (Box 2)
      - Projects
        - Project Status Sheets 1970 (Box 2)
        - Inventory 1970 (Box 2)
        - Summary Report of the Ad Hoc Housing Committee 1971 (Box 2)
        - Novi, Michigan Project 1968-1971, 2 folders (Box 2)
        - Proposal for Elmwood II undated (Box 2)
        - Report on Low-Cost Housing Technology in Elmwood II Park 1967 (Box 2)
        - Elmwood's People Rebuild 1968 (Box 2)
        - Elmwood Park 2, Draft Report 1967 (Box 2)
        - Nagel Housing Files 1969-1975, 2 folders (Box 3)
        - Community Projects Information Center 1968, 1970 (Box 3)
        - Industrialized Housing Competition 1968 (Box 3)
      - Publications
        - Brochure undated (Box 3)
        - Newsletter 1972 (Box 3)
    - Mayor's Youth Opportunity Council, City of Detroit
      - "The Detroit Happening," 1968 (Box 3)
      - Index to Proposals and Programs Screened and Granted by Youth Opportunity Council 1968
        - Publishing and Distributing Brochures (Box 3)
        - Girls Physical Education (Box 3)
        - Pilot House-Teen Center (Box 3)
        - Afro-American Culture, Arts, Recreation (Box 3)
        - Community Safety Patrols (Box 3)
        - "Earn and Learn"
          - Accounts, 2 folders (Box 3)
          - Photographs (Box 3)
        - Inner City-Suburban Youth Study Project (Box 3)
        - Neighborhood Improvement and Employment Project
          - Reports (Box 3)
          - Photographs (Box 3)
        - Photography Project
          - Reports (Box 3)
          - Photographs (Box 3)
        - Teen Program, Employment, and Recreation
          - Photographs (Box 3)
        - Youth Village-Teen Program (Box 3)
        - Arts, Crafts, Library (Box 3)
        - Teen Activity Center (Box 3)
        - Outdoor Recreational Supervision -- 12th Street
          - Reports (Box 3)
          - Photographs (Box 3)
        - Moore School Summer Project (Box 3)
        - Store Front Recreation Center (Box 3)
        - Friendship House-Youth Program (Box 3)
        - Vest Pocket Parks (Box 3)
        - Multi-Service Centers: Employment and Recreation (Box 3)
        - Eastside Committee on Youth Behavior (Box 3)
        - Student Volunteer Corps (Box 3)
        - Supplement-Project #8 (Box 3)
        - Summer Science Research Program (Box 3)
        - Festival of Arts (Box 3)
        - Cultural Arts Workshops, 2 folders (Box 3)
        - Transportation (Box 3)
        - Teen Drop-In Center Staff (Box 3)
        - Neighborhood Clean-Up, Arts and Crafts (Box 3)
        - Boys and Girls Club (Box 3)
        - Neighborhood Improvement Project
          - Accounts (Box 3)
          - Photograph (Box 3)
        - Community Recreation and Education Project (Box 3)
        - Children and Youth Safety Program (Box 3)
  - Ann Arbor
    - Model Cities Program
      - Progress Report 1969 (Box 4)
      - Mid-Planning Report 1969 (Box 4)
      - First Year Action Plan 1970-1971 (Box 4)
    - Avalon Housing
      - Articles of Incorporation and By-Laws 1992 (Box 4)
      - Shelter Association and Avalon Housing Committee 1992 (Box 4)
      - Board of Trustees Meetings
        - 1992 (Box 4)
        - 1993 (Box 4)
        - 1994 (Box 4)
        - 1995 (Box 4)
        - 1996 (Box 4)
        - 1997 (Box 4)
        - 1998 (Box 4)
      - Special Board Meeting on Arbordale 1998 (Box 4)
      - Notes for Presentation on Avalon Housing 1997 (Box 4)
      - Financial Records 1993-1998 (scattered) (Box 4)
      - Events 1995-1998 (scattered) (Box 4)
      - Federal Awards Supplemental Information 1994, 1995 (Box 4)
      - Correspondence 1992-1999 (scattered) (Box 4)
      - Clippings 1992, 1995 (Box 4)
      - Publications 1994-2004 (scattered and undated) (Box 4)
      - Compensation Committee 1997, 1998 (Box 4)
      - Agency Strategy 1999 (Box 4)
      - Hiring 1993-1995 (Box 4)
      - Personnel Manual undated (Box 4)
    - Ann Arbor Advisory Planning Council 1979, 1983 (Box 4)
- Ombudsman
  Three large sections compose the Ombudsman series: Assistant Superintendent of Ann Arbor Public Schools, publications, and the University of Michigan. The first section has official reports from Potts's office. The agency was responsible for addressing citizens' grievances to the school district. Recurring issues are race, class, and gender. This section also has a wealth of text speeches that Potts delivered during his tenure. The second section contains two of Potts's publications on the topic of Ombudsmanship. The third section is an assortment of items from his time as a University of Michigan graduate student, including a bound copy of his dissertation.
  - Assistant Superintendent for Human Relations and Community Services, Ann Arbor Public Schools
    - Reports
      - Annual Reports, Office of Ombudsman
        - 1971-1975 (Box 4)
        - 1975-1978 (Box 4)
        - 1978-1981 (Box 4)
        - 1981-1984 (Box 4)
      - Recommendations for Combating Racism 1971 (Box 4)
      - Recommendations for Implementation of the Report on Humanness in Education 1971 (Box 4)
      - An Over-View Activities of the Office of Human Relations Ombudsman Ann Arbor Public Schools School Year 1970-71 1971 (Box 5)
      - Summary Types of Grievances Through the Office of Human Relations Ombudsman School Year 1970-71 1971 (Box 5)
      - Recommendations for Implementation of a Comprehensive Affirmative Action Program in the District 1972 (Box 5)
      - The Impact of Planning Decisions Upon Schools and Educational Policy 1972 (Box 5)
      - Functions and Programs, (scattered and undated) (Box 5)
      - Humanness in Education 1974-1975 (Box 5)
      - Title IX: Self Evaluation 1976 (Box 5)
      - A Discussion Document on a Rationale and Planning Guide for Desegregation in the Ann Arbor Public School District 1976 (Box 5)
      - Affirmative Action Policy & Procedures for Contractors and Vendors 1976 (Box 5)
      - International Bar Association Ombudsman Committee 1976 (Box 5)
      - Desegregation Data and Analysis: Options for Educational Change 1978 (Box 5)
      - EEO Policy Analysis Ann Arbor Public Schools 1978 (Box 5)
      - New and Planned Housing Developments within the Ann Arbor School District 1979 (Box 5)
      - Report of the Citizens' Advisory Committee on Racial Balance & Educational Opportunity 1979, 2 folders (Box 5)
      - Black English -- A Current Educational Issue: The Ann Arbor Experience 1979 (Box 5)
      - A Preliminary Draft of a Plan for Improving Educational Opportunity and Improving Racial Balance in the Ann Arbor Michigan School District 1980 (Box 5)
      - "Remember the Ladies!" A Handbook of Women in American History 1980 (Box 5)
      - Progress Report Office of Assistant Superintendent -- Human Relations & Community Services 1980-81 School Year 1981 (Box 5)
      - Summary Types of Grievances Through the Office of Human Relations & Ombudsman 1982 (Box 5)
      - Gender and Ethnic Equity Goals and Plans for Implementation 1982 (Box 5)
      - An Administration Perspective on Suspensions in the Ann Arbor Schools 1982 (Box 5)
      - Ann Arbor Public Schools Year End Report 1983 (Box 5)
      - District Gender and Ethnic Equity Assessment 1982-1983 School Year: A Progress Report on the Implementation of the 1981-82 Assessment 1983 (Box 5)
      - District Gender and Ethnic Equity Assessment 1983-84 School Year 1984 (Box 5)
      - Community Services in the Ann Arbor Public Schools 1985 (Box 5)
      - Two-Year Operational Plan 1985 (Box 5)
      - Progress Report on Action Plans 1986 (Box 5)
      - Action Plan 1986 (Box 5)
      - Race/Ethnic/Gender Composition Study in Special Education 1986 (Box 5)
    - Speeches from Ombudsman Office
      - 1970 (Box 5)
      - 1971 (Box 5)
      - 1972 (Box 5)
      - 1973 (Box 5)
      - 1974 (Box 5)
      - 1975 (Box 5)
      - 1977 (Box 5)
      - 1978 (Box 5)
      - 1979 (Box 5)
      - 1980 (Box 5)
      - 1981 (Box 5)
      - 1983 (Box 5)
      - 1984 (Box 5)
    - Topical
      - Thank You Letters 1971-1985 (scattered) (Box 5)
      - Harvard Graduate School of Education Training 1983 (Box 5)
      - Miscellaneous 1980-1985 (scattered) (Box 5)
      - Minority Recruitment and Retention undated (Box 5)
      - Reorganization of Ann Arbor Schools 1984 (Box 5)
      - Cleary College 1984-1987 (scattered) (Box 5)
      - Retirement 1986 (Box 5)
      - Discussion with Transportation Personnel 1988 (Box 5)
  - Publications
    - Robert L. Potts, "Educating the School Community About School Authority and Student Rights." In Student Behavior, Rights and Responsibilities and the Fair Administration of Discipline: Conference Proceedings April 1-2, 1974, Ed. Charles D. Moody et al. (Ann Arbor: University of Michigan, 1974) (Box 5)
    - Robert L. Potts, "Where Will it Go From Here?" Chalkboard ( February 1979 ) p. 1. (Box 5)
  - University of Michigan, Horace H. Rackham School of Graduate Studies
    - Student Files 1974-1982 (scattered) (Box 5)
    - Robert L. Potts, "Ombudsmanship in Public Elementary and Secondary School Districts." Dissertation, University of Michigan, 1975. (Box 5)
- Episcopal Priest
  The Episcopal Priest series is organized into three groups. The first consists of Potts's sermons delivered from 1977-1994, non-inclusive, and contains both text and audio files. The second grouping represents religious ceremonies from 1979-1996 that Potts officiated, the majority of which were eulogies and marriages. Included are the texts of speeches in addition to a sampling of the note cards he used. The final grouping in the series is a list of topical files. Particular highlights include the United Ministries in Higher Education (Eastern Michigan University chapter), Potts's installation as Archdeacon, records of the McGehee Fund, and a personal diary kept during the later years of his life. This grouping offers a unique insight into the role of the church as an agent of social and economic justice in Southeastern Michigan.
  - Sermons
    - Textual
      - Christmas 1977-1992 (scattered) (Box 6)
      - Easter 1982-1994 (scattered and undated) (Box 6)
      - Epiphany 1983-1997 (scattered and undated) (Box 6)
      - Lent 1983-1994 (scattered and undated) (Box 6)
      - Occasional
        - 1982 (Box 6)
        - 1986 (Box 6)
        - 1988 (Box 6)
        - 1989 (Box 6)
        - 1990 (Box 6)
        - 1991 (Box 6)
        - 1992 (Box 6)
        - 1994 (Box 6)
        - 1995 (Box 6)
        - 1996 (Box 6)
        - Undated (Box 6)
    - Sound cassettes of sermons
      - 1990-1991 (Box 6)
      - 1991-1992 (Box 6)
    - Poems, Hymns, and Quotes undated (Box 6)
  - Eulogies, Marriages, and Ceremonies 1979-1996 (scattered and undated), 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Topical Files
    - Messages and Meanings of the Christian Life by Robert L. Potts 1987 (Box 6)
    - Grace Episcopal Church Seventy-fifth Anniversary Celebration 1992 (Box 6)
    - Carter Metropolitan Christian Methodist Episcopal Church Twenty-fifth Anniversary Celebration 1970 (Box 6)
    - United Ministries in Higher Education, Eastern Michigan University
      - 1988 (Box 6)
      - 1989 (Box 6)
      - 1990 (Box 6)
      - 1991 (Box 6)
      - 1992 (Box 6)
    - Archdeacon Issues 1987-1989 (Box 6)
    - Archdeacon Installation 1988 (Box 6)
    - Log of Activities 1990-1991 (Box 7)
    - Diary 1997-2002 (scattered) (Box 7)
    - Installation of Nathan Dwight Baxter 1992 (Box 7)
    - Diocese of Michigan, A Sesquicentennial History 1983 (Box 7)
    - St. Andrew's Episcopal Church 1994 (Box 7)
    - Vestry 1988-1990 (Box 7)
    - The Ordering of Reverend Robert Lester Potts to the Sacred Order of Priests 1964 (Box 7)
    - Invocations for public meetings, Board of Education (undated) (Box 7)
    - The McGehee Fund
      - 1992 (Box 7)
      - 1995 (Box 7)
      - 1996 (Box 7)
      - 1997 (Box 7)
      - 1998 (Box 7)
      - 1999 (Box 7)
      - 2000 (Box 7)
      - 2001 (Box 7)
      - 2002 (Box 7)
      - Undated (Box 7)
    - Correspondence 1970-1997 (Box 7)